Louis H. Cohen Papers VHP2005/17
CCSU Veterans History Project
Louis H. Cohen Papers
Bulk, 1940-1945
1940 - 1945, 2005
VHP2005/17
CCSU Veterans History Project
70.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
Cohen, Louis H., 1915 -
Biographical/Historical note
Louis H. Cohen enlisted in the National Guard in 1940 just before the draft began. In September of 1940, when the National Guard was federalized, he became part of the U.S. Army. He went to Camp Blanding, FL for basic training in early 1941 where his unit, which consisted of many other members of the National Guard from New Britain, CT, was trained mostly for the infantry. War was declared on December 7, 1941, while Cohen was attending additional training at Camp Blanding. He was then transferred to Camp Shelby, MI to train as a gunner. Cohen describes how the soldiers had to train using sticks because they had no real equipment. It was at this time that he decided to take the test for Officer Candidate School so that he could be a quartermaster. He did his training as quartermaster at Fort Lee, VA, and after 90 days, he received his commission and became the 2nd lieutenant in charge of a 60-75 man platoon in the 249th Quartermaster Battalion, which was an all black battalion with white officers in charge. In May of 1943, Cohen's battalion shipped to North Africa, where he oversaw the unloading of supplies that were to go to the French for the Lend-lease program. Although, his unit was a service battalion and not a combat battalion, they were involved in the invasions of Sicily and Anzio, Italy, where Cohen's platoon lost men from the constant shelling. Cohen describes what it was like to command a platoon under the conditions that they met with, and some of the other duties he had to carry out, such as censoring their mail. After a year overseas, Cohen was promoted to 1st lieutenant and he was rotated back to the United States in order to teach officer classes at the Quartermaster School. Cohen spent the remainder of his service in Camp Lee teaching operations. He was discharged in September of 1945, and he returned to New Britain, CT where he worked in the family grocery business until 1968.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
Arrangement note
Series I: Presonal Papers
Series II: Military Documents
Series III: Publications
Series IV: Multi-Media
United States. Army. Quartermaster Battalion, 249th .; United States. Army.; Algiers (Algeria); Camp Blanding (Fla.); Camp Shelby (Miss.); Fort Lee (Va.); Gioia del Colle (Italy); Interviews; Lend-lease operations (1941-1945); Manuscript; Oran (Algeria); Photographs; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Italy; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - Louis Cohen promotion to Corporal, Nov. 4, 1941; VHP2005/17.I.1
  - Interview Synopsis, Sep. 7, 2005; VHP2005/17.I.2
- Series II: Military Documents, VHP2005/17.II
  - FM 21-100, Soldier's Handbook (Basic Field Manual), 1940; VHP2005/17.II.1; 261.0 pages
- Series III: Publications, VHP2005/17.III
  - Handbook of Motor Vehicle used by the United States Armed Forces, VHP2005/17.III.1; 97.0 pages
  - Christmas greeting at Quartermaster School, Camp LEE, VA, circa 1940s; VHP2005/17.III.2; 97.0
  - Pointer for Infantry Troop Leaders, circa 1940s; VHP2005/17.III.3; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Quartermaster Training Service Journal, July 1945; VHP2005/17.III.4; 17.0 pages
  - Brochure of School Department of Quartermaster School, Camp Lee, VA, n.d.; VHP2005/17.III.5; 10.0 pages
- Series IV: Multi-Media, VHP2005/17.IV
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2005/17.IV
    - Company I, 169th Infantry. Camp Blanding, FL, Jun. 7, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.1
    - Company I, 169th Infantry. Camp Blanding, FL, Jun. 7, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.2
    - Capt. Harry Jackson Company Commander, NC, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.3
    - Ringrose (first name unknow) digging a foxhole with a mattock, NC, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.4
    - Infantry on maneuvers, NC, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.5
    - Ed Woods, NC, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.6
    - In the flood resulting from hurricane. Louisiana maneuvers (military exercises), LA, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.7
    - The flood resulting from hurricane, Louisiana maneuvers, LA, August 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.8
      General note
      Persons L– R:Gilbert Julian, Phil McGuiness, “Peppy” Glynn
    - Captain Jackson, flood resulting from hurricane, Louisiana maneuvers, LA, August 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.9
    - Phillip McGuiness and Gilbert Julian. The flood resulting from hurricane, Louisiana maneuvers, LA, August 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.10
    - Unknown soldiers sunning his feet during Louisiana maneuvers, LA, August 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.11
    - Louisiana maneuvers, Kisatchie National Forest, LA, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.12
      Persons L—R(foreground): Mike Demuseo, Gilbert Julian, Phillip McGuiness, Unknown, J. Burava
    - Soldiers posting with M1903 Springfield Rifle and mattock, Louisiana maneuvers, LA, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.13
      Persons L—R: Sgt Hooge, Brown
    - latrines, Louisiana maneuvers, LA, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.14
    - Latrine with rock ock used as floor plate, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.15
    - J. Burava of Kensington on rest period two days before Louisiana maneuvers ended, LA, 1941; VHP2005/17.IV.16
    - Canal Street, New Orleans, LA, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.17
    - A view of Alabama from train going to Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.18
    - Pitching tents in Gulfport, MS (near Camp Shelby), 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.19
    - GMC CCKW, U.S. Army cargo truck, loading troops leaving Gulfport, MS for Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.20
    - Parade Review. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.21
    - Passing in Review - Regimental Parade. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.22
    - Parade Review. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.23
    - Parade Review. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.24
    - A military band - parade Review. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.25
    - “Present Arms Drill” Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.26
    - Chapel at Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.27
    - Sgt Bryzgel. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.28
    - Riccio, Piccoli, LaPine. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.29
    - Riccio, Larese, unknown Sgt. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.30
    - Yacobellis, Sargent(from Plainville, CT), Sanford. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.31
    - LaPine (first name unkonw) Camp Shelby, MS 1942, VHP2005/17.IV.32
    - Larese and Company Assembly, Company Street. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.33
    - Sczcepanik (first name unknow) Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.34
    - Company Street, Mess Hall in center background. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.35
    - Soldiers resting on company street, Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.36
    - Our Company Street. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.37
    - Riccio — a Mail Clerk. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.38
    - Yacabellis in front of bulletin board. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.39
    - Four soldiers, Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.40
      L—R(Rear):Museo, unknown. L-R(Front): two unknown
    - Soldiers on parade. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.41
    - Soldiers and Cooks. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.42
    - Burava at Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.43
    - LaPine at Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.44
    - Sgt. Yelenak at Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.45
    - Colwick (from Plainville, CT) Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.46
    - Soldiers in conversation. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.47
    - Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.48
    - Company Street. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.49
    - Company Latrine. Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.50
    - Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.51
    - Camp Shelby, MS, 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.52
    - Sgt. Louis Cohen and Bernard Gutman at Officer Candidate School(OCS) - “90 Day Wonder”. Camp Lee, VA, October 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.53
    - Louis Cohen writing a letter. Officer Candidate School, Camp Lee, VA, October 1942; VHP2005/17.IV.54
    - Louis Cohen in Sicily, Italy, 1943; VHP2005/17.IV.55
    - Louis Cohen in Sicily, Italy, 1943; VHP2005/17.IV.56
    - Second Lieutenant Louis Cohen in Palermo, Sicily, 1943; VHP2005/17.IV.57
    - Louis Cohen on Anzio Beach, Italy, 1944; VHP2005/17.IV.58
    - Louis Cohen holding a censored letter, 1944; VHP2005/17.IV.59
    - Quartermaster School NCO Division instructors. Camp Lee, VA, 1944; VHP2005/17.IV.60
    - Louis Cohen at home, Sep. 7, 2005; VHP2005/17.IV.61
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2005/17.IVb
    - Oral history interview, Sep. 7, 2005; VHP2005/17.IVb.I; 1.0 dvd; Hurst, James P. (Disk DVD VHP2005/17, Box VHP Interview #1)